Hi, this is Matt Baker. On this channel,
I've covered hundreds of different
family trees, but one thing I've never
done is covered the chart of a non-human
family. Well, that's about to change
because today I'm going to show you the
family tree of the J pod, a group of 27
southern resident orcas who live in the
Salish Sea near my home in Vancouver.
Orcas, also known as killer whales, even
though they are not actually whales but
rather dolphins, are some of the most
intelligent non-human animals on the
planet. Resident orcas in particular
live in complex matriarchal societies,
use tools, play games, show emotions,
and even have language dialects that are
unique to their pods. These orcas are
called residents in order to distinguish
them from the other main type of orca in
the Pacific Northwest, the transients.
You see, originally it was thought that
only the resident orcas actually resided
in the Salish Sea, whereas the transient
orcas just passed through. However, we
now know that that's not true because
the transients are here just as much as
the residents are. For this reason, the
transients are now increasingly known as
Bigg's orcas, named after Michael Bigg,
an early orca researcher. There are
still some major differences between the
two types though, so much so that they
do not interbreed or even communicate
with each other. For instance, Bigg's
orcas mainly eat marine mammals, travel
in smaller groups that often change, and
have simpler language. Whereas residents
mostly eat fish, travel in stable family
groups called pods, and have a more
complex language. The resident orcas who
live near Vancouver are known as
southern residents, in contrast to the
northern residents who live, well, to
the north. The southern residents are
critically endangered, and as of 2026,
there are only 74 of them. They travel
in three distinct pods, J, K, and L. J,
which is the family we'll be looking at
today, is the smallest and currently has
only 27 members.
Now, before I jump into their tree, I
want to shout out today's sponsor,
Ground News, which is the website and
app that I use to keep up to date with
what's happening around the world, not
just all the big political conflicts,
but smaller stuff, too, like the latest
on Timmy the whale, who was stranded off
the coast of Germany for over a month.
What Ground News does is pull headlines
from hundreds of different sources from
all over the world, including
newspapers, podcasts, and websites. It
then categorizes them on a continuum
from left to right, so that you get to
look at the same story from different
angles. So, for example, you can see
that this left-leaning source emphasizes
the sad nature of the story and the
human compassion it sparked, whereas
this right-leaning source emphasizes the
private initiative that is trying to
save the whale. Of course, the best
thing about Ground News is the charts,
such as this one showing the bias
distribution, or this one showing which
sources are the most factual based on
third-party rankings, or this one
showing what percentage of the sources
are independently owned or owned by the
government or big business.
Ground News also has a blind spot feed,
which highlights stories that one side
of the spectrum is barely covering at
all. So, you're not just trapped inside
the version of events your usual media
wants to feed you.
So, don't wait. Subscribe now by going
to ground.news/charts
or by using the link in the description
or pinned comment. If you use that
address or link, you will get 40% off
unlimited access to their Vantage plan.
Again, that's ground.news/charts.
Okay, let's now jump into the J pod
family tree. I'm going to start with
Mobi Doll, who was the very first
resident orca to be studied. Prior to
Moby Doll, orcas were mostly feared and
hated by humans, with fishermen often
shooting at them whenever they
encountered one. But then in 1964, this
attitude started to change. It began
when the Vancouver Aquarium commissioned
a team to kill an orca so that they
could use it as a model for a new
sculpture. But after being harpooned,
the young orca survived, and therefore
the aquarium decided to keep it in a pen
so that it could be studied as well as
viewed by the public. Nicknamed Moby
Doll, the male orca sadly survived in
captivity for only 4 months. But by the
end of those 4 months, the public
perception of orcas had changed. In that
short period of time, scientists learned
that they were far more intelligent than
previously thought, and the public came
to see that they were actually quite
gentle.
Unfortunately though, the idea of
protecting orcas within their natural
environment was still a long way off.
And instead, for the next decade or so,
there was a rush to capture orcas and
sell them to aquariums. The next J pod
member to suffer this fate was Shamu, a
young female who was captured in 1965
and sold to SeaWorld in San Diego, where
she became the first orca to be forced
to perform live shows. This original
Shamu lived for only 6 years in
captivity. But for the next 45 years,
SeaWorld continued to use the name Shamu
to promote their shows using other
captive orcas.
Now, we don't know the exact genealogy
of either Moby Doll or Shamu, but they
were probably either siblings or cousins
of J1 and J4, who were from the same
generation. As you'll notice throughout,
each orca studied in the wild now has a
numerical designation as well as a
nickname. So, for example, J1 was also
known as Ruffles because he had a
distinctive ruffle on his dorsal fin. He
and Granny, designated J2, were the
first two members of the J pod to be
studied in their natural habitat. They
were usually seen together, so it was
originally assumed that they were mother
and son, although DNA later proved this
not to be the case. Granny did, however,
have a daughter nicknamed who was
the mother of Kenauk and Samish. Kenauk
was the only other member of J pod to be
captured and sold to SeaWorld. He,
unfortunately, died after just two
years. His sister, however, lived to be
42 and is today the namesake of the J14
matriline, a group of six orcas who all
descend from her. You see, currently the
pod is divided into six groups called
matrilines based on their matrilineal
ancestry. As I mentioned earlier,
resident orcas are matriarchal, which is
why all of the main lines on this chart
are pink, pink representing females and
blue males.
It's easy to deduce who an orca's mother
is because orca children tend to stay
close to their mothers even as adults.
Figuring out who the father is, however,
usually requires DNA. This is why the
paternal ancestry, represented on this
chart by dotted lines, is only shown for
the more recent generations. Although,
take note that we don't yet know the
paternity of the most recent births as
they have not yet been tested. So, for
example, all of Samish's surviving
children were fathered by an orca named
Mega from the L pod. As you can see, he
fathered a lot of children during the
'90s and 2000s. The only other male
known to father this many children is
Ruffles, who I mentioned earlier. In
fact, he was the father of Samish and
hence the grandfather of her three
children.
Now, all of the orcas in the J14
matriline have indigenous names given to
them by the Coast Salish people who live
in the same area. So, Haischka means
thank you. See each in means younger
sibling. Telim Engis means singing
grandchild. And Swea Kosh means reason
for hope. You see, she was born after
the death of a young calf in this
matriline called J55 or Beatle, whose
exact mother and sex is unknown. As for
Suttles, she was named after Wayne
Suttles, a linguist who specialized in
the Coast Salish language. And Suttles'
daughter, J63, the most recent J pod
member, has yet to be named as she just
turned 1 year old last month. And
traditional naming ceremonies usually
don't take place until sometime after an
orca's first birthday. Now, before I
move on to the next matriline, I want to
go back to Granny for a moment because
she actually lived until 2016. And at
the time of her death was thought to be
105 years old. However, this was later
disputed when a postmortem calculated
that her age at death was more likely to
be somewhere in between 65 and 80 years
old. Regardless, she did live to an old
age and was observed helping to raise
her great-grandchildren, something very
rare in animal species. Basically, only
humans, orcas, and a few other cetacean
species have females that go through
menopause. So, this is yet another
reason why orcas are so special.
Okay, we're now going to look at the J11
and J19 matrilines, both of which likely
descend from J4, nicknamed Mama, who, as
I mentioned earlier, was born around the
same time as Moby Doll and Shamu.
Although not 100% for certain, she is
thought to have been the mother of both
J11, Blossom, who passed away in 2008,
and J19, Shachi, who is still living.
Blossom currently has four surviving
descendants. The two males, Blackberry
and Mako, were fathered by Ruffles,
whereas Suchi was fathered by an unknown
male. Although we do know that that same
unknown male also fathered J26, Mike.
Mako was only five years old when his
mother Blossom died, so he was actually
mostly raised by his sister Suchi. Suchi
and Mako are the only two J-Pod members
to have been given Japanese names. Both
names being Japanese words for whale. In
2019, Tofino was born and later named
after a town on Vancouver Island. She
was originally thought to have been the
daughter of Suttles, but was later
determined to be the daughter of Suchi.
Moving on to the J19 matriline, which is
led by its namesake J19, or Shachi.
Although she is not the oldest female in
the J-Pod, ever since Granny died, it
has been Shachi who has been understood
to be the overall matriarch of the
entire J-Pod. Her only surviving child
is a female named J41, or Eclipse,
fathered by Ruffles. In 2015, she
herself became a mother at just 10 years
old, giving birth to J51, Nova. This was
unusual, as most orcas have their first
child closer to age 15. Eclipse then
went on to have two more children, J58,
Crescent, in 2020, and the
yet-to-be-named J62 in 2024.
We now come to the J16 matriline, which
is named after and still led by J16, aka
Slick. Although this branch can actually
be traced back one more generation to
Slick's mother, J7, who was known as
Sucia, after an island in Washington
state. Slick, who once had a brother
called J3 Merlin, is currently the
oldest J-Pod member, being about 7 years
older than Shachi. Nowadays, she has
three surviving children and no
grandchildren. It is in this matriline
that we get our first examples of
incest, something that is not normally a
common thing with orcas, which sadly
means that it is likely the result of
their numbers being so low. So,
basically, J26 Mike, who was named after
Michael Biggs, is the father of his
sister J42 Echo, which means that Mike
made it with his own mother. In addition
to this, Mike also made it with his
other sister J36
Alki to produce J52 Sonic, but sadly,
Sonic passed away at age two.
The following year, this matriline lost
yet another youngster when J50, aka
Scarlet, died at age three. She had
originally been thought to be the
daughter of Alki, but was later
confirmed to be the daughter of Slick,
which is notable because Slick was 42
years old at the time, making her the
oldest known orca to give birth.
Scientists were aware that Scarlet was
sick for about a year before her death
and tried to help by giving her
antibiotics by dart. Incredibly, exactly
1 year to the day after her death,
Slick, Mike, Alki, and Echo were seen
leaving the rest of the J-Pod behind and
traveling to the exact spot where
Scarlet died in order to pay their
respects.
The final two matrilines, J17 and J22,
are both thought to have descended from
J9, nicknamed Neah, who may actually
have been older than Granny. Neah gave
birth to J5 Saratoga, who in turn gave
birth to J17, nicknamed Princess
Angeline, after the daughter of Chief
Seattle. Princess Angeline lived until
2019 and near the end of her life was
taken care of by the Lummi Nation of
Washington state who would row out close
to her and feed her fresh salmon. The
Lummi Nation have a special relationship
with the Southern Resident Orcas going
back thousands of years. In fact, in
their language, they call them Kw'elho
Mentshen which literally means our
relatives who live under the waves.
Princess Angeline's first child was a
daughter called J28 or Polaris. And it's
here that we get another rare example of
incest. You see, Polaris' father was
Ruffles, but the father of her firstborn
child J46 or Star was also Ruffles.
Unfortunately, Polaris died in 2016 due
to complications arising from the birth
of her second child J54, Dipper, who
also died shortly thereafter. The most
senior female in this matriline is
therefore now J35 or Tahlequah, which
means mother of waters. These days she
is perhaps the most well-known member of
the J pod. This is because although she
has two living children, both males, J47
Notch and J57 Phoenix, she also lost two
children, both females. The first was T
Tahlequah, which means little Tahlequah.
When she lost the child shortly after
birth in 2018, she carried the child's
body on her nose for 17 straight days
traveling over 1600 km in an act of
grieving that drew international
attention. In 2020, she gave birth to
J57 who was named Phoenix in order to
symbolize rebirth and hope. But then in
2024, she lost another daughter and once
again carried her on her nose, this time
for 11 straight days.
The final and smallest matriline is J22,
which has only two members. J22,
nicknamed Oreo, and her second son J38,
Cookie. Previously, Oreo did have a
sister called J20, Ewok, both of them
being the daughters of J10, Tahoma. But
sadly, Ewok died in 1998, two years
after giving birth to J33, Rhapsody. At
this point, Rhapsody was adopted by
Oreo, who had just given birth to J34,
Double Stuff. Unfortunately though, both
Rhapsody and Double Stuff died at age
18. Rhapsody due to pregnancy
complications, and Double Stuff from
being mistakenly hit by a vessel. So, as
you can see, between the years 2014 and
2024, the J pod lost 13 members,
including seven young calves, which just
goes to show why they, as a group, are
so endangered. However, with the recent
births of J62 and J63, both of whom have
now made it past their first birthdays,
things are looking a bit better.
Fortunately, now that we have a better
understanding of just how amazing these
fellow citizens of Earth are,
governments are starting to put into
place several more measures to help
protect them, such as limiting noise
from vessels, increasing their food
sources, and reducing water pollution.
Now, before I go, I do want to mention a
few other famous orcas who were not
members of J pod, but are fairly well
known. First of all, there's Keiko, who
starred in the 1993 movie Free Willy.
Now, while the orca in the movie was
portrayed as being from the Pacific
Northwest, Keiko, who played Willy, was
actually from the waters near Iceland.
He was captured there in 1979 at the age
of three and then went on to live in
aquariums in Iceland, Canada, and Mexico
before starring in the film Free Willy.
Now, because of the movie, a movement
was started to actually free the real
orca who played Willy, aka Keiko. It
took some time to prepare him for this,
but Keiko was eventually released back
into the waters near Iceland in 2002.
Although he continued to be closely
monitored after this. Unfortunately, he
died after just one year of freedom.
Then there's Tilikum, another Icelandic
orca, who this time was featured in the
2013 documentary Blackfish. Blackfish
highlighted the trauma experienced by
orcas in captivity, as well as the
dangers they pose to humans when treated
this way. Tilikum in particular was
involved with the death of three humans,
two of whom were trainers. The
documentary led to a massive public
backlash against SeaWorld, where most
captive orcas in the US live, resulting
in the company announcing in 2016 that
they would be immediately halting their
breeding program and slowly phasing out
all orca shows.
Finally, there's Lolita, also known as
Tokitae or Toki. She was a member of L
pod and was captured in 1970 during the
infamous Penn Cove operation, the
largest ever orca capture in history. At
Penn Cove, more than 80 orcas were
herded into nets, including Granny and
Lolita. But whereas Granny was released
because she was deemed too old, Lolita,
along with six others, were kept and
sold to aquariums. Sadly, five orcas
died that day, something that was hidden
at the time, but then came to light
several months later. This sad event led
to a turn in public opinion though, and
by 1976, orca captures were banned in
both BC and Washington. It was too late
for Lolita though, and she ended up
living at the Miami Seaquarium for the
next 53 years. Near the end of her life,
there was a movement to have her return
to her native waters, but unfortunately,
she died in 2023 before this could
happen. However, her ashes were given to
the Lummi Nation, who scattered them
into the Salish Sea during a special
ceremony.
Okay, so that was a look at the family
tree of the J Pod, who are fortunately
now treated much better than they were
in the past. Hopefully, in the future,
we humans will continue to develop
better relationships with those we share
this planet with. Thanks for watching.